Register of the Aleksei Aleksandrovich Fon-Lampe Papers, 1918-1926
Hoover Institution Archives
Aleksei Aleksandrovich Fon-Lampe Papers,
1918-1926
28003
Fon-Lampe, A. A.
10 manuscript boxes (4.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, memoranda, orders, newsletters, clippings, leaflets, maps, pamphlets, and printed matter, relating to operations of the offices of the Russian Military Agent in Germany and the Russian Military Representative to Hungary, Russian counterrevolutionary activities, political events in Russia, and activities of Russian civilians and military personnel in Europe. Includes the office files of the delegation of the Russian Society of the Red Cross for Relief to Prisoners of War, 1919-1922.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1928.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (20 reels).
Access Points
Rossiiskoe obshchestvo krasnogo kresta.; Russia (Territory under White armies, 1918-1920). Armiia--Officers.; Russia (Territory under White armies, 1918-1920). Dobrovol'cheskaia armiia.; Vooruzhennye Sily na IUgie Rossii.; Prisoners of war.; Refugees.; Russians in foreign countries.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.
Biographical Note
1885 Born, Lithuania
1903 Graduated from Russian Military Academy
1903-1917 Served in Tsarist army
1921-1926 Military Representative of the Commander-in-Chief of the Russian Army to the Government of Hungary
1922-1926 Russian Military Agent in Germany Chief of the Second Division of R.O.V.S. (Russkii Obshe-Voinskii Soiuz)
1945-1948 Head of local unit of French Red Cross, Lake Constance
1960 Died
Series Description
- Office File Of The Russian Military Agent In Germany, 1918-1926 (Box No. 1-7.)
  Announcements, circulars, correspondence, financial statements and receipts, information bulletins, memoranda, notes, orders, reports and staff lists, arranged as listed. Constitutes the files of General Nikolai A. Monkewitz (June-August 1919); Colonel Alexander F. Brant (mid-1919 to early 1920); Lieutenant-General Ivan A. Holmsen (early 1920 to mid-1922); and Colonel Alexei A. von Lampe (mid-1922 to 1926). Includes letters and orders signed by Generals Nikolai N. Yudenitch, A. E. Denikin, P. N. Wrangel, P. A. Kusonskii, E. K. Miller, and P. N. Shatilov.
- Office File of the Russian Military Representative to the Government of Hungary, 1921-1926 (Box No. 8-9.)
  Correspondence, financial statements, orders, and staff lists, arranged as listed. con-stitutes the files of Esaul Vladimir A. Ilawaisky, Assistant To The Military Representative to the Government of Hungary, and Colonel Alexei A. Von Lampe, who simultaneously held the posts of Military Agent in Germany and mIlitary Representative To The Government Of Hungary. Includes letters and orders signed by Generals P A. Kusonskii, E. K. Miller, and I. A. Holmsen.
- Office File of the Delegation of the Russian Society Of The Red Cross for Relief to Prisoners-of-War, 1919-1922 (9-10.)
  Correspondence, arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent or name of organization. General Dmitri N. Potosky was chief of the delegation from January to May 1919, after which its functions were assumed by the Russian Military Mission in Germany.
- Subject File, 1919-1926 (Box No. 10.)
  Letters, newspaper clippings, reports, communiques, pamphlets, leaflets, maps, lists, newsletters, and information bulletins, arranged alphabetically by subject.
Container List
- OFFICE FILE OF THE RUSSIAN MILITARY AGENT IN GERMANY, 1918-1926
  - Announcements, 1925 (Box 1.)
  - Circulars, 1919-1926
  - Correspondence, 1919-1926
    - General, 1919-1925
    - Unidentified, 1919-1925
    - Al'tfater, Major-General D., 1921
    - Avalov, Prince Pavel M., 1919-1924
    - Banque J. Xydias, 1922-1923
    - Bioro po Dielam Russkikh Biezhentsev v Baden-Baden (Bureau for the Affairs of Russian Emigres in Baden-Baden), 1922
    - Bioro Russkoi Pechati v Konstantinopol (Bureau of the Russian Press in Constantinople), 1920-1921
    - Brant, Colonel Alexander F., 1920-1922
    - British Military Mission, Berlin, 1919
    - Brun, Leonid A., 1923
    - Deutsches Rotes Kreuz (German Red Cross), 1926
    - French Embassy in Germany, 1920
    - Glavnoupolnomochennyi Glavnokomanduiushchavo Voorzhennymi Silami Iuga Rossii po Voennym i Morskim Dielam (Chief Representative of the Commander-in-Chief of the Armed Forces in South Russia for Military and Naval Affairs), 1920-1926
      - Materials issued by the Russian Military Mission in Germany and received by the Chief Representative, 1920-1924
      - Materials issued by the Chief Representative and recieved by the Russian Military Mission in Germany, 1920-1926
        - 1920
        - 1921
        - 1922
        - 1923
        - 1923-1926
    - Globachev, Major-General N. (General of the Volunteer Army; Representative Conducting Negotiations for the Evacuation of Prisoners-of-War from Poland), 1919
    - Golovine, General N., 1926
    - Informatsionnaia Gruppa "D i L" (Information Group "D and L"), 1922-1923
    - Interallied Commission for the Repatriation of Russian Prisoners-of-War, 1919
    - Josefovich, Yakov D., 1924-1926
    - Kartashev, Colonel Peter V. (Leader of the Cossacks in Germany), 1922-1924
    - Khomutov, Colonel A., 1920
    - Kondzerovsky, Lieutenant-General Peter K., 1925
    - Kovenskoe Obshchestvo Vzaimopomoshchi Invalidov i Voennosluzhashchikh byvshei Rossiiskoi Armii (Kovensky Mutual Aid Society for Invalids and Former Servicemen of the Russian Army), 1924-1925
    - Krasnov, General Peter N., 1920-1922
    - Kriudner-Struve, Baron Alexander A., 1924-1925
    - Kutepov, General Alexander P., 1923-1926
    - Lager' Viunsdorf (Camp Wuensdorf), 1919-1922
    - Legation Royale de Hongrie (Royal Legation in Hungary), 1922
    - Lillienberg, Baron Fr. Abele von, 1922-1925
    - Lloyds National Provincial Foreign Bank Ltd., 1924
    - Makhrov, Major-General Peter S., 1922-1924
    - Military Agent in Belgium, 1919-1922
    - Military Agent in Bulgaria, 1922
    - Military Agent in Czechoslovakia, 1919-1924
    - Military Agent in Denmark, 1919-1926
      - Materials issued by the Russian Military Mission in Germany and received by the Military Agent in Denmark, 1919-1924
      - Materials issued by the Military Agent in Denmark and received by the Russian Military Mission in Germany, 1919-1926
        - 1919
        - 1920 (Box 2.)
        - 1921
        - 1922
        - 1923
        - 1924
        - 1925
        - 1926
    - Military Agent in Great Britian, 1919
    - Military Agent in the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes, 1920-1924
    - Military Agent in Poland, 1919-1920
    - Military Agent in Sweden and Norway, 1919-1924
    - Military Agent in Switzerland, 1919-1920
    - Military Agent in Turkey, 1920-1923
    - Miller, Lieutenant-General Yevgeny K., 1922-1926
      - Materials issued by the Russian Military Mission in Germany and received by the office of General Miller, 1922-1926
      - Materials issued by the office of General Miller and recieved by the Russian Military Mission in Germany, 1922-1924
    - Ministr Inostrannykh Diel (Minister of Foreign Affairs, Russia), 1919-1920
    - Mission Militaire Francaise (French Military Mission, Berlin), 1919
    - Oldenburg, Sergei S., 1923
    - Pervyi Armeiskii Korpus (First Army Corps), 1924-1926
    - Politicheskaia Kantselliariia Glavnokomanduiushchavo (Political Office of the Commander-in-Chief), 1922-1925
    - Pravlenie Soiuza Vzaimopomoshchi byvshykh Ofitserov Rossiiskikh Armii i Flota (Directorate of the Mutual Aid Association of Former Officers of the Russian Army and Navy), 1921-1926
    - Pravlenie Soiuza Vzaimopomoshchi Sluzhivshikh v Rossiiskom Flotie (Mutual Aid Association of Veterans of the Russian Navy), 1924-1926
    - Predsiedatel' Tsentra Ob"edinennykh Obshchestvennykh Sibirskikh Organizatsii (Chairman of the Center for the United Siberian Voluntary Organizations), 1919 (Box 3.)
    - Predsiedatel' Vysshavo Monarkhicheskavo Sovieta (Chairman of the Supreme Monarchist Council), 1922-1925
    - Reichministerium des Innern (German Ministry of the Interior), 1920-1922
    - Representative of Ataman Semenov in Germany, 1920
    - Representative of Prince Kiril, 1922-1923
    - Rode, V. P., 1922-1926
    - Ronzhin, Lieutenant-General Ivan A., 1921-1925
    - Rul' (periodical), 1922-1926
    - Russkii Akademicheskii Soiuz v Germanii (Russian Academic Association in Germany), 1924-1926
    - Russkii Komitet o Biezhentsakh v Bavarii (Russian Committee for Emigres in Bavaria), 1922-1924
    - Russkii Komitet v Varshavie (Russian Committee in Warsaw), 1923
    - Rossiiskoe Predstavitel'stvo v Germanii (Russian Delegation in Germany), 1920-1926
    - Rossiiskaia Voennaia Missiia - Grazhdanskii Otdiel (Russian Military Mission - Civil Division), 1919-1920
    - Semenovsky, L. G., 1924-1925
    - Shatilov, General Pavel N., 1923-1926
    - Shtaba Glavnokomanduiushchavo Russkoi Armii (Staff of the Commander-in-Chief of the Russian Army), 1919-1926
      - Materials issued by the Russian Military Mission in Germany and received by the Staff of the Commander-in-Chief, 1919-1926
        - 1919
        - 1920
        - 1921
          - January -July
          - August -December
        - 1922
        - 1923
        - 1924
        - 1925
        - 1926
      - Materials issued by the Staff of the Commander-in- Chief and recieved by the Russian Military Mission in Germany, 1919-1926
        - 1919
        - 1920
        - 1921 (Box 4.)
        - 1922
        - 1923
        - 1924
        - 1925
        - 1926
    - Skalon, Mikhail N., 1924-1925
    - Soiuz Russkikh Ofitserov Reinskoi Provintsii (Association of Russian Officers in the Rhineland), 1923-1924
    - Soiuz Russkikh Ofitserov Uchastnikov Voiny (Association of Russian Officers Who Participated in the War), 1921-1926
    - Soiuz Russkikh Ofitserov v Avstrii (Association of Russian Officers in Austria), 1925-1926
    - Soiuz Russkikh Uveshnykh Voinov v Germanii (Association of Russian Crippled Soldiers in Germany), 1921-1926
    - Soiuz Uchastnikov I Kubanskovo Generala Kornilova Pokhoda (Association of Participants in the First Kuban Campaign of General Kornilov), 1924-1925
    - Soiuz Vzaimopomoshchi Ofitserov Inzhenerykh, Tekhnicheskykh i Zheleznodorozhnykh Voisk (Mutual Aid Association of Officers from the Engineer, Technical, and Railroad Detachments), 1925-1926
    - Soviet Ob"edinennykh Ofitserskikh Obshchestv v Korolevstvie S.K.S. (Council of the United Officers' Societies in the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes), 1922-1926
    - Tsentral'noe Pravlenie Obshchestva Russkikh Ofitserov General'novo Shtaba (Central Administration for the Society of Russian Officers of the General Staff), 1922-1926
    - United States Military Mission, Berlin, 1919
    - Unkovsky, Ivan S., 1924-1926
    - Upravlenie Lagerei Russkikh Biezhentsev v Garts (Directorate of Russian Refugee Camps in Hartz), 1920-1921
    - Upravlenie po Dielam o Voennykh i Voennoplennykh (Directorate for the Affairs of Servicemen and Prisoners-of-War), 1919
    - Velio, Baron Vladimir I., 1923-1924 (Box 5.)
    - Verband Gegen Den Bolschewismus (Union Against Bolshevism), 1920
    - Voennyi Predstavitel' Glavanokomanduiushchavo Russkoi Armii pri Pravitel'stvie Frantsuzskoi Respubliki (Military Representative of the Commander-in-Chief of the Russian Army to the Government of France), 1920-1921
    - Voennyi Predstavitel' Verkhovanavo Pravitelia pri Soiuznykh Pravitel'stvakhi i Knomandovanii (Military Representative of the Regent Supreme to the Allied Governments and General Headquarters), 1919-1920
      - Materials issued by the Russian Military Mission in Germany and received by the Military Representative of the Regent Supreme, 1919-1920
      - Materials issued by the Military Representative of the Regent Supreme and received by the Russian Military Mission in Germany, 1919-1920
        - 1919
        - 1920
    - Yudenitch, General Nikolai N., 1919-1920
    - Zarubezhnyi Soiuz Russkikh Voinnykh Invalidov (Association of Russian War Invalids Abroad), 1923-1926
    - Zavieduiushchii Voennym Snabzheniem (Director of Military Supply), 1920-1921
  - Financial statements, receipts, etc., 1921-1926
  - Information bulletins, 1922-1925
  - Memoranda, 1919
  - Notes relating to the dispatch and arrival of information, 1919-1925
  - Orders, 1924, 1926
    - Chief of the Organization to Protect the Interests of Russian Emigres in Germany, 1924
    - Chief of the Second Division of R.O.V.S., 1926
  - Reports on the political situation in various countries, 1918-1926
    - Baltic states, 1919
    - Bulgaria, 1921-1922
    - Czechoslovakia, 1921-1922
    - Far East, 1921, 1924
    - France, 1921-1924
    - Georgia, 1921
    - Germany, 1921-1924
      - General, 1923-1924
      - Periodic Surveys of the political situation in Germany, 1921-1924
        - 1921
        - 1922 (Box 6.)
          - January -April
          - May -December
        - 1923
          - January -June
          - July -December
        - 1924
    - Great Britain, 1922
    - Hungary, 1921-1923
    - Near East, 1921
    - Poland, 1919
    - Scandinavia, 1920-1925
    - Soviet Russia, 1918-1926 (Box 7.)
      - General, 1918-1926
      - Informatsionnoe Otdelenie Shtaba Glavnokomanduiushchavo Russkoi Armiei (Information Division of the Staff of the Commander-in-Chief of the Russian Army), 1921-1922
      - Military Agent in Czechoslovakia, 1921-1922
      - Military Agent in France, 1923
      - Military Agent in Germany, 1922-1925
        - 1922
        - 1923
        - 1924
          - January -October
          - November -December 1925
      - Military Agent in the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes, 1923-1925
    - Ukraine, 1919-1924
    - Yugoslavia, 1922
  - Staff lists, n.d.
- OFFICE FILE OF THE MILITARY REPRESENTATIVE OF THE COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF OF THE RUSSIAN ARMY TO THE GOVERNMENT OF HUNGARY, 1921-1926
  - Correspondence, 1921-1926 (Box 8.)
    - General, 1921-1924
    - Gerua, Alexander V., 1924
    - Glavnoupolnomochennyi Glavnokomanduiushchavo Russkoi Armii po Voennym i Morskim Dielam (Chief Representative of the Commander-in-Chief of the Russian Army for Military and Naval Affairs), 1922-1924
    - Hungarian Minister of the Interior, 1922
    - Hungarian Minister of War, 1922
    - Lukin, Yevgeny D., 1923-1924
    - Malam, Vladimir V. (Representative of the Russian Red Cross in the Kingdom of Hungary), 1922-1926
    - Marushevsky, Vladimir V., 1923-1924
    - Military Agent in Czechoslovakia, 1923
    - Military Agent in Germany, 1922-1924
      - Materials issued by the Russian Military Mission in Germany and received by the Assistant to the Military Representative in Hungary, 1921-1924
      - Materials issued by the Assistant to the Military Representative in Hungary and Russian Military Mission in Germany, 1922-1924
        - 1922
        - 1923
        - 1924
    - Military Agent in the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats, and Slovenes, 1922-1924
    - Military Agent in Turkey, 1922-1923
    - Miller, Lieutenant-General Yevgeny K., 1922-1924
    - Obshchestvo Vzaimopomoshchi Chlenov Russkano Monarkhicheskavo Ob"edinenniia v Korolevstvie Vengerskom (Mutual Aid Society of Members of the Russian Monarchist Union in the Hungarian Kingdom), 1922-1923
    - Paleolog, Sergei N., 1924
    - Raevsky, Captain Nikolai V., 1925-1926
    - Rosen, Baron Vladimir G., 1924-1926
    - Russkoe Monarkhicheskoe Ob"edinenie v Korolevstvie Vengerskom (Russian Monarchist Union in the Hungrian Kingdom), 1922
    - Schmidt, General Nikolai V., 1922-1924
    - Shtaba Glavnokomanduiushchavo Russkoi Armii (Staff of the Commander-in-Chief of the Russian Army), 1922-1924
    - Soiuz Russkikh Invalidov v Vengrii (Association of Russian Invalids in Hungary), 1922
    - Soiuz Russkikh Ofitserov v Korolevstvie Vengrii (Association of Russian Officers in the Kingdom of Hungary), 1924
    - Sokolov, Colonel Anatole A., 1922-1926
    - Studencheskaia Gruppa Gallipoliitsev v Vengrii (Student Group from Gallipoli in Hungary), 1924 (Box 9.)
    - Vadkovsky, Vasily V., 1922
    - Vengerskaia Kazachei Stanitsa (Hungarian Cossack Village), 1922-1925
    - Viaz'mitinov, Lieutenant-General, 1923-1924
    - Volkonsky, Prince Peter P. (Russian Diplomatic Representative in Hungary), 1920-1923
    - Yalyshev, Constantine V., 1922
    - Zhukovsky-Volynsky, Colonel Nikolai I., 1925-1926
    - Zubov, Colonel Yuri, 1926
  - Financial statements, 1923
  - Orders, 1922-1924
  - Staff lists, n.d.
- OFFICE FILE OF THE DELEGATION OF THE RUSSIAN SOCIETY OF THE RED CROSS FOR RELIEF TO PRISONERS-OF-WAR, 1919-1922
  - Correspondence, 1919-1922 (Box 9.)
    - General, 1919
      - Materials issued by the Russian Red Cross, 1919
      - Materials received by the Russian Red Cross, 1919
    - American Red Cross, 1919
    - Boguslavsky, Colonel, 1919
    - Lager' Bad-Blenkhorst (Camp Bad-Blenhorst), 1919-1920
    - Lager' Khelmshtedt (Camp Helmstedt), 1919
    - Lager' Klaustal' (Camp Clausthal), 1919
    - Lager' Kottbus (Camp Cottbus), 1919-1922
    - Lager' Kvedlinburg (Camp Kvedlinburg), 1921
    - Lager' Miunkhenberg (Camp Muenchenberg), 1919
    - Lager' Neishtadt (Camp Neistadt), 1919
      - February
      - March
      - April-May
    - Lager' Pliassenburg (Camp Plassenburg), 1919
    - Lager' Scheuen (Camp Scheuen), 1921-1922
    - Lager' Vambek (Camp Wahmbeck), 1919
    - Lager' Vetsliar (Camp Wezler), 1919
    - Lager' Vil'deman (Camp Wildeman), 1919
    - Lager' Zal'tsvedel' (Camp Salzwedel), 1919
    - Pervyi Ofitserskii Eshelon (First Officers's Echelon), 1919 (Box 10.)
    - Rossiiskoe General'noe Konsul'stvo v Kopengagenie (Russian General Consulate in Copenhagen), 1919
- SUBJECT FILE, 1919-1926
  - Bolshevik agents in Europe, 1919-1926 (Box 10.)
  - Communist Party of the United States, 1924
  - Court of Honor, 1920-1922
  - Cossacks, 1926
  - Kluyev, General N., 1919
  - Mitarevsky, Vladimir de, 1919-1920
  - Nikolaevskoe Kavaleriiskoe Uchilishche (Nikolaievsky Cavalry School), 1922
  - Obshechestvo Russkikh Ofitserov General'navo Shtaba (Society of Russian Officers of the General Staff), 1922-1926
  - Requiem for All Who Fell on the Field of Battle in the Great War (August 3, 1924), 1924)
  - Rosenberg, Captain von, 1920
  - Russia - Civil War
    - Baltic states, 1919
    - Northwest Front, 1919-1920
  - Russian Army, general, 1919-1924
  - Russian emigre newspapers, 1919-1926
  - Russian-German commercial relations, 1919-1920
  - Russian officers' unions, 1919-1926
  - Russian prisoners-of-war and emigres in Germany, 1919-1923
    - General, 1919-1922
    - Passports, correspondence relating to, and applications, for, 1922-1923
  - Russisch-Deutschen Gesellschaft (Russian-German Society), 1919
  - Russkaia Missiia pri Mezhdusoiuznoi Voennoi Kontrol'noi Kommissii (Russian Delegation to the Interallied Control Commission), 1919-1920
  - Soiuz Russkikh Ofitserov v Reinskoi Provintsii (Association of Russian Officers in the Rhineland), 1923-1924
  - Verband Russischer Flieger in Deutschland (United Russian Aviators in Germany), 1925-1926
  - Wrangel, Baron Peter N., (Commander-in-Chief of the Russian Army), 1922-1923